THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
Kitty cat, kitty cat
小小猫呀
She cries and cries
那孩子
Wondering
哭呀哭的
Where that child is
不知在何处？
Will you play with me, sir?
可否请大人与小的对弈？
How could I say no?
既然是可爱女儿的请求
It's my beloved daughter's request.
岂有理由拒绝呢？
We'll play by the standard rules for five matches.
胜负是普通规则的五回战
Whoever wins three matches first wins.
也就是先取得三胜的一方获胜
What should my disadvantage be?
让子要如何呢？
Which piece should I get rid of?
我该拿掉哪个棋子呢？
There's no need for that.
没有必要
She should just accept.
老实接受不就好了吗？
Let's decide what to bet on.
比起让子 要不要先决定赌注呢？
Wow, getting straight to the point!
那真是正合我意
If I win, you'll become my child, right?
我赢的话 你就来当我女儿吧？
-You promised not to say anything. -Yes, but…
您答应过不插嘴的吧？
That is fine. But I'm under an employment contract.
无妨 但小的仍是受雇之身
So it'll be after my time is up.
得等到期满之后才行
An employment contract? He really hired you?
受雇之身？他真的雇用了你吗？
Yes.
真的
But in return, if I win…
相对地 若小的赢了
Will you buy out a courtesan from the Verdigris House?
您愿意帮绿青馆的一位娼妓赎身吗？
I didn't expect you to say that.
没想到你会提这个
I won't say who,
我不会说是谁
but Grams is looking for a way to get rid of a certain courtesan.
只是因为老鸨 想将上了年纪的娼妓请走罢了
I see, that's how you'll play.
来这招啊？
If that's what you want, I'll have to say yes.
如果这就是你的条件 我也只能接受了吧
That's all you want?
这样就够了吗？
I'll add two more rules, then.
那么 再追加两条规则吧
It smells like a strong distilled liquor.
闻起来感觉是浓烈的蒸馏酒
I have a really bad feeling about this.
有种特别不祥的预感
And what is that?
这是什么？
A little bit of this is medicine.
服下少许的话是药
Three mouthfuls, and it's a strong poison.
若服下三口 便会成为剧毒
I'll pour this liquid into three cups,
我会将这小瓶倒入三个杯子中
and mix it up so you don't know which cup.
然后打乱顺序 使其无法分辨
After each match, the winner chooses a cup,
每局分出胜负时 由赢家选出一杯
and the loser drinks it.
输家则要喝掉那一杯
That's the first rule.
这是第一条规则
Her ideas are so frightening.
她的想法也太可怕了
And the second rule is, no matter what the reason is,
第二条规则 无论是什么理由
if you forfeit the match, you lose.
只要放弃棋局就算输 请加入这两条规则
Is that all right?
可以吗？
Yes, that's fine.
无所谓的
Is she trying to throw him off balance?
这是为了扰乱对方吗？
True, a normal person might flinch at that. However,
的确 若是对上 一般人也许有用 但是…
her opponent is a Sir General known for being eccentric.
对手是人称奇人的军师大人
I can't imagine him getting agitated by such a threat.
我不认为这点干扰就能够乱其阵脚
What is she thinking?
她究竟在想什么？
She lost again.
她又输了
That's her second loss in a row!
这下已经二连败了
She challenged a general known for being a chess master
竟然用象棋挑战未尝败战的军师
so I thought she had some skill, but…
我还以为她多少有点擅长
It seems she only knows the rules
看来是只知道规则
and has no experience in playing matches.
但并没有实战经验
She already drank two cups.
她已经喝两杯了
She seemed to enjoy drinking them, so I can't tell if it's poisoned or not.
因为都喝得津津有味 根本分不出来是不是毒酒
May I start the third match?
第三局由我先攻可以吗？
Sure, of course.
好啊 请吧
What is she thinking?
她到底在想什么啊？
We all know how the third match will end.
第三战的结果已经一目了然
If the two cups she already drank had poison inside,
若刚刚喝下的两杯放了毒
it's too dangerous to drink the third cup.
要喝下第三杯就太危险了
How much of this current situation has Lakan analyzed?
这个状况 不知道罗汉掌握了多少呢？
Checkmate.
将军
You got me.
我输了
I know you let me win, but it's still a win.
虽然您手下留情 但赢了就是赢了 没意见吧？
I can't make my daughter take poison, even by accident.
毕竟再怎么说 我也不能让女儿喝下毒药啊
Which will you choose for me?
你要选哪一杯呢？
Choose whatever you'd like.
请您随意选吧
Does the medicine have any taste?
那个药有味道吗？
You'd notice the bad taste right away after one swallow.
喝下一口后 觉得难喝便是了
Lakan is allowed to lose twice.
罗汉能够输上两局
If one cup of the two tastes different,
只要有一杯味道不对
he'll know that his daughter won't take any poison.
便能知道女儿会不会喝到毒药了
He lost deliberately for that purpose.
他是为此故意输掉这一局的
He really is a shrewd man.
果然是个精明的男人
I'll choose this, then.
那我就选这杯吧
It tastes bad.
真难喝啊
He drank the poison!
是有下毒的
Now, the Apothecary won't drink the poison for her third cup.
如此就不用担心 药师会喝到第三杯毒药了
This also means
这也代表
that Lakan won't have to keep losing on purpose anymore.
罗汉没有必要再输一局了
Now, the Apothecary can never win.
药师没有胜算了
If I win, you'll become my child, right?
我赢的话 你就来当我女儿吧？
Also, I feel hot.
话说回来 真热啊
What's going on?
这究竟是…
I thought the poison wouldn't harm anyone with one cup!
你不是说只喝一杯药酒不会有事吗？
I know you hate him.
就算你再怎么讨厌他
-But I didn't think you'd poison him! -It's medicine.
-我也没想到你真的下毒 -是药啊
They say sake is the best medicine, after all.
都说酒为百药之长嘛
Sake? What do you mean?
酒？什么意思？
Sir Jinshi.
壬氏大人
-It looks like he's just drunk. -What?
-他似乎只是醉了 -什么？
He's an extreme lightweight.
这个人的酒量很差哦
Now that I think about it,
这么一说
he's always drinking juice. I've never seen him drink sake.
他平常总是喝果子露 从没见过他喝酒
So what was the liquid you poured in?
那你刚刚倒进去的液体是？
It was alcohol. All right, then.
是酒精 好了
Let's carry this man out,
赶快把这男人搬出去
and have him pick out a flower from the brothel.
让他去挑选青楼的花吧
Ever since I was born, I couldn't distinguish people as individuals.
我出生之后 便无法分辨人脸
It wasn't just confusing my wet nurse as my mother.
不仅将奶娘和母亲认错
I couldn't even distinguish between a man and a woman.
也分不出男女
My father got fed up with me, saying that I would be useless,
父亲厌弃我 认为我是无用之人
and started visiting his extramarital lover regularly.
从此流连于情妇之处
My mother was desperate to get my father back.
母亲则拼命想将那样的父亲挽回身边
That was how I was able to immerse myself in go and chess,
就这样 虽然身为名家长子
and live freely, despite being the first son
但我却能沉迷于 学艺习得的围棋和象棋
of a noble family.
活得自在奔放
Don't remember people by their face.
不是靠长相 而是靠声音、举止
gestures, and body type.
和体格等来记住别人
I'm sure you would enjoy chess.
你的话 就用象棋吧
Only my uncle understood me.
能够理解我的 唯有叔父
Thanks to my tactless yet talented uncle,
多亏了活得笨拙但才能优秀的叔父
I was able to see people's faces as chess pieces.
我渐渐能把人的脸看作是棋子
When I saw my uncle's face as a Chariot,
当我能将叔父的脸看作是车时
I truly understood that he was a talented and intelligent man.
我重新体认到他果然是名优秀的男子
After I grew up, even though I was untalented in the art of war,
成人之后 明明我不会武艺
I was appointed to be a leader right away because of my background.
却因为家世显赫 而突然被命为军队长官
Even if I was weak,
即使自己能力很差 但只要能善用部下便绰绰有余
Playing chess with real people as its pieces
将人当作棋子的象棋
was merely a captivating game to me.
肯定是最有意思的游戏
THE VERDIGRIS HOUSE
（绿青馆）
While I continued to be unbeatable in work and in chess,
无论是工作或游戏都未尝一败
I ended up playing against a famous courtesan when I visited a brothel.
这时我陪人进了青楼 与传说中的娼妓进行对决
Amongst the sea of whites and blacks,
在无数的黑白之间
those fingertips had a vibrant glow.
唯有那儿散发出艳丽的光芒
Her name was Fengxian.
女子的名字叫做凤仙
An unbeatable courtesan at a brothel, versus an unbeatable military man.
在青楼未尝一败的娼妓 和在军府里未尝败一败的我
No matter who lost, the audience would be captivated.
无论是哪边落败 观众都会看得很高兴
She is good for sure.
她确实是很强
Even so, she is merely a frog in a well.
但终究不过是井底之蛙
I lost?
我输了？
She dominated me completely.
而且还毫无还手之力
When was the last time I lost like this?
上次输成这样是什么时候来着？
So this is what a human face looks like.
原来人的脸是长这样啊
Her eyes are like a balsam fruit, which could pop
她的双眼宛如凤仙花的果实
with a single touch, keeping people at a distance…
只要轻轻一触便会爆开 不让人亲近的眼神…
I won't lose next time.
这次我可不会输
For several years after that, I only met her to play
在那之后 我们不断 反复下着围棋和象棋的幽会
go and chess.
不知持续了几年
Fengxian, who was born at the brothel,
凤仙出生于青楼
had a personality only shaped by pride.
是个一身只有傲骨的女子
I do not have a mother.
我没有母亲
There was a woman who gave birth to me,
倒是有生下我的女子
but in the pleasure district, courtesans cannot be mothers.
在花街 娼妓是当不了母亲的
Talented courtesans,
才华出众的娼妓
once they become popular enough, become harder to purchase.
受欢迎到了一定程度 便会开始惜而不卖
This was also true of Fengxian.
凤仙也是其中一人
Though her stern attitude was not popular amongst most customers,
尽管她严厉的态度 并非所有人都能接受
there were some with strange tastes who enjoyed that.
但有一部分爱好者却十分中意
Her price kept increasing more and more,
身价也随之水涨船高
and I could only afford to see her once every three months.
三个月见一次面都已捉襟见肘
A balsam flower and… What is that?
凤仙花和…这叫什么？
Wood sorrel.
酢浆草 又叫做猫足
It's a fresh medicine that works against poison and insect bites.
这是能够应付解毒和虫咬的生药
Just like the balsam flower,
和凤仙花一样
if you touch its ripened fruit, the seeds burst and fly away.
只要触碰成熟的果实 便会爆开使种子飞散
I see, how interesting.
哦 真是有意思
When can you come next?
大人下次何时过来？
In three months' time.
再过三个月后
I see.
我明白了
It was around that time that I heard of Fengxian being bought out.
就在那段时间 我听说了凤仙赎身的事情
Her price kept increasing more and more in the bidding war amongst her fans.
凤仙的身价 由于爱好者的竞相出价一再抬高
Though I had climbed the ranks as a military man,
虽然作为武官飞黄腾达
my step brothers had taken the right to inherit the family title.
但我家中的继承地位 已被同父异母的弟弟夺走
I could never compete with those prices.
实在是拿不出那么多银两
What if we bet on something today?
偶尔来赌一场如何？
If you win, I'll give you anything you'd like.
你赢的话 你要什么我都给你
If I win, I'll take anything I want.
我赢的话 我要什么你都得给
Which board would you like to play with?
请大人选喜欢的棋盘吧
That's when a terrible idea crossed my mind.
突然有个糟糕的想法闪过我的脑海
-You'd like to play go, then? -Yes.
-您选围棋 对吧？ -对
-Meimei. I want to focus on the match. -Yes, ma'am.
-梅梅 我想专心下棋 -是
Before we realized it, our hands were placed together.
回神时 手已交迭在一起
Fengxian spoke no sweet words.
凤仙没有半句甜言蜜语
I spoke none, either.
我也不擅说情话
In many ways, we were very similar.
某方面来说 我们两人算是同类
I want to play go.
我想下围棋
I had thought I wanted to play chess too.
我心里则是想要下象棋
Kitty cat
小小猫呀
She cries and cries wondering
那孩子 哭呀哭的
Where that child is
不知在何处？
The little birds
什么都不晓得的
That know nothing
小小鸟儿们
Flew higher and higher
向着遥远的天空
Up in the sky…
一去不复返
Three months after that, my talented uncle lost his position.
三个月后 优秀的叔父遭到罢黜
You became a doctor in the rear palace, and now you're expelled?
还以为你成了后宫的医官 结果你却被流放了？
You disgrace the family name!
真是丢尽家族的脸！
He was talented, but remained tactless.
明明很优秀 却总是活得很笨拙
You were close with him.
你跟那家伙交情很深吧？
Leave this house and study abroad for a while!
滚出家里 去游学一阵子吧
-Study abroad? -It's a needed precaution.
-游学？ -以防万一
-But… -What is it?
-但是… -怎么了？
No, it's nothing.
不 没什么
I could not betray my father, who was both my parent and a boss.
父亲既是亲人也是上司 我没办法违逆他
It was then that Fengxian wrote to me saying she would not be bought out.
也在那时 我收到凤仙的信 说赎身之事已经破局了
I had falsely assumed that I could return
我以为大概半年之后
in six months' time.
就能回来
Back then…
那个时候…
I had not imagined that
我没有料到
it would take me three years to return home.
自己花了三年的时间才能回来
All these are letters from Fengxian?
凤仙寄了这么多…
Dirt? No, are these branches?
泥土块？不 树枝吗？
And there's two of them?
而且还有两个？
No! This is…
不对 这是…
Finger slicing…
断指
I had heard that the practice was popular as a curse.
我听说时下流行着这种诅咒
The reason she ended up not being bought out…
赎身之所以破局的原因
The other small finger that was inside that bag…
袋子里装的另一个幼小指头是…
How could I not realize?
为什么没有察觉到？
I only had go and chess in mind.
我的脑子里满是围棋和象棋
I couldn't even arrive at such a simple answer!
所以才会连这么简单的答案都没想到
THE VERDIGRIS HOUSE
（绿青馆）
Where is Fengxian?!
凤仙在哪儿？
You! Fengxian is not here anymore!
你这家伙 凤仙已经不在了！
Why are you here after all these years!
事到如今你还来做什么？
You left her for three years!
整整三年不见人影
I bet you don't even care about what happens
你不知道失去价值的娼妓
when a courtesan loses her value!
最后会沦落到什么下场吗？
If I had thought for a little bit, I would've realized it.
只要稍微动动脑子就能明白的
Why her buying out offer was rescinded.
赎身之事告吹的原因
Inside Fengxian's belly was…
就是因为凤仙的腹中…
What happens to a courtesan
让店家名声扫地
when she dishonors her brothel and her trust and value plummets to the ground?
信用和价值都跌落谷底的娼妓 最后沦落的境地
Like a nighthawk, she receives any customer,
便是只能像暗娼一样接客
and eventually…
最终…
No matter how much I lament, time won't turn back.
无论我再怎么悲叹 时光都无法倒回
Everything happened because
一切都是因为…
I was so short-sighted. It's all my fault.
我思虑不周所造成的
This is… The Verdigris House.
这儿是…绿青馆吗？
Are you awake?
大人醒了吗？
Meimei.
梅梅
Some person of nobility brought you here.
某位贵人派人将您送来这儿的
You look very unwell.
话说回来 您的脸色真是吓人
Your face is both red and blue.
不知道该说是红还是青呢
I didn't plan on being like this.
我也没料到会搞成这样子啊
I didn't think that the drink was so strong.
没想到那个酒这么浓烈
Meimei used to be an apprentice to Fengxian.
梅梅曾经是 凤仙身边的见习娼妓小丫头
I used to play with Meimei quite a lot.
我过去也时常和梅梅下棋
When told she had potential, she seemed embarrassed but happy.
只要夸她有天分 便会变得扭扭捏捏的
Speaking of…
话说…
What's wrong?
怎么了？
No, it's nothing.
不 没什么
-Here you are. -Thanks.
-来 请用 -谢谢
So bitter! What is this!
好苦！这是什么啊？
Maomao made that.
好像是猫猫调制的
Mix, mix, mix.
我捣…
I see, Maomao made this.
原来 是猫猫啊
Also, Maomao made this box.
还有 这个盒子也是猫猫给的
A dried rose?
干燥的玫瑰？
Even after it has died, you can preserve its form.
我都不知道枯萎后 还能保持这种形状呢
Big Sis Meimei.
梅梅姐姐
Excuse me, sir.
恕我先告退了
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next Episode, "Jinshi and Maomao."
下一集 《壬氏与猫猫》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：杨易